[Music]
【音乐】 标题：用编程语言共同治愈我们的地球
so as long as here we are in the
很高兴来到我们的计算机科学
computer science and AI laboratory
以及AI实验室
let me ask perhaps by a show of hands
让我先随机调查一下
from the audience how many of you know what a programming language is
观众中知道编程语言是什么的请举手
okay this is MIT after all so maybe I shouldn't be surprised
好的，毕竟这里是MIT，所以也没那么令人诧异
how many of you have programmed the computer again
第二个问题，你们之中有多少人 是亲自编写过程序的？
I know this is this is a great audience this
这是一群很棒的观众
this is MIT
毕竟这里是MIT。
so I'm a co-founder co-inventor of a programming language
我自己是一门编程语言的共同创始人和共同发明者
known as Julia perhaps some of you have
这门语言叫Julia，也许你们当中有些人
used it and this language is becoming
有用过它，这种语言目前正在
increasingly popular for all of the
越来越流行，越来越受到
various kinds of models that will be
各种各样科学计算模型的青睐
coming up in the various talks today the
其中就包括我今天要提到的
climate models the economic models the
气候模型，经济模型
various political models and so forth so
以及各种政治模模型等等
let me say a little bit about myself
接下来，让我简单介绍我自己
first of all I'm a mathematician I'm a
首先，我是数学家，我也是
computer scientist here in this building
在这座大楼里的一位计算机科学家
I mentioned that I'm a co-inventor of
我刚刚提到我是
the programming language Julia
编程语言Julia的共同发明者
I have a wife and two children and the cutest little Corgi on the planet
我有一个妻子和两个孩子，以及全世界最可爱的小柯基犬
what I'm not, to be honest, I'm not a climate scientist
另一方面，老实说，我既不是气候科学家
I'm not an economist I'm not a policy maker
也不是经济学家，也不是政策制定者
I'm not even completely sure why I'm even in this room
我甚至不完全确定我为什么会身在此处
except we are all on this planet together
唯一的理由，也许是 我和你们都在同一个星球上
so about programming languages
关于编程语言
humans talk to computers specifying the instructions that automate our world
人们常常通过指令，告诉计算机自动地计算一些刻画世界的模型
with programming language
这种指令就是编程语言
the climate models the economic models
包括气候模型，经济模型，
the political models are they're all implemented as instructions to computers
政治模型等等，都是用这些电脑指令来实现的
I co-founded this programming language
我共同创建了此程序的计算机Julia
Julia that allows not only
这种语言不仅可以
humans to talk to computers but
让人们告诉计算机该做什么
it allows humans to talk to humans about
它更可以让人与人之间相互
their intent on the computer
使用编程语言交流他们的想法
so we all have this vision of we program a
在之前，我们都有同样的经验
computer maybe you sit in your own little room and a little silo somewhere
当我们编程时，我们会坐在自己的 小房间，小仓库，或者其他地方
and you specify these arcane instructions that you tell the computer what to do
然后我们编写一些晦涩难懂的指令 告诉计算机该做什么
I have a vision of the
而我想做的，是让这种编程语言
ability to have other humans know what
能够让别的人类也能知道
it is you're telling the computer and what they can do
你在告诉电脑做什么
you might think that it's a common occurrence that
你可能会认为 这是常见的情况
programming languages can, you know,
不管是什么编程语言
somebody writes a program and a person can look at it and see what's going on
只要有人写了一个程序 另一个人只需要看看程序，就能知道 它是用来做什么的。
but I assure you it's anything but
但事实上，我可以确定完全不是这样
I've taken a look at some climate models some of the codes out there
我之前看了一些气候模型的代码
and I assure you it is very very very difficult
我可以负责的告诉你
perhaps you've programmed
也许你们都编过程
many of you have raised your hand
我记得刚刚你们很多人都举了手
there are languages out there there's that
现在已经有很多编程语言
some of you may have heard of like Java and C++
你们也许听过类似于C++或者Java这样的编程语言
these are languages that are very very common in the business world
它们在真正的商业环境下 非常非常常见
there are other languages that are easy to use
还有一些语言是以其易用性著称
they're scratch, Python was invented as a
比如有Scratch，Python等
language to become easy to use and
特别Python,从一开始就被
because it was so easy to use it became
设计的十分易于使用
extremely popular and now it's very very widely used
因此Python现在十分流程，被广泛使用
so the common wisdom has always been for programming languages is
一般人总是认为 选择编程语言的时候
that there is you could have an either or nor,
总是需要包括一部分取舍
either you can have a programming language that's easy to program
要么你可以选择一个 易于使用的编程语言
but you'll pay the price
但选择他们也有代价
somehow the programs will execute much more slowly
它们常常会运行的十分缓慢
you will lose out on performance
你将会因此牺牲一部分程序性能
the other possibility is you
另一种可能是
it's a much more difficult endeavor
你选择一个更困难的编程语言
you have to be much more skilled at programming but then you can get the performance
花费更多的时间来编写一个程序 不断打磨编程技巧 以此来达到更好的性能。
we set out to show that it wasn't one or the other
而我们想做的是告诉大家，不必在易用性和性能间取舍
you can have your cake and eat it too
两者可以兼得
the Julia programming language lets you
Julia编程语言可以让你
program readily but also gets you performance
轻松地编程，但与此同时也可以让您
if you look at the climate
获得优秀的性能。比如在气候模型方面
models you find some of the time that
你在看代码的时候会发现
the codes are unavailable a lot of the
很多时候代码都是无法获得的
time scientists write a paper they put
科学家们一般都关注于论文
together some powerpoints they might put
他们可能聚在一起看一些幻灯片
together some output of their code but
交流一些代码的输出结果，但代码本身
the code itself is unavailable for you to look at
别人是获取不到的
okay this is what we call closed source
没错，这就是我们所说的闭源代码
other times
另外一种情况是
the codes are available you can look at them but they're not easy to look at
代码虽然可以看到，但是就算要看懂代码 也不是个容易的事
but very often what people are doing is
由于人们在大多情况下
what's called low-level programming
是在做底层编程（low-level programming）
you specify very specifically what you want the computer to do
人们需要写很多很特殊的指令
perhaps you get performance by doing that
这也许提升性能
but you lose complete sight of what it is from a high level that's going on
但这会抹去很多 从高层次看来的宏观上的理解
what continues to surprise me as a Julia co-founder
作为Julia的联合创始人，我心中的一直有一个梦想
is that a programming language can let humans talk to humans
我希望编程语言可以让人类也能与人类进行交流
a programming language can create community
一种编程语言应该能创建社区
can actually create social action
一种编程语言应该唤起社会的行动
it opens very very human possibilities
它能够打开更多更多人类的可能性
so my own story is a testament to the power of language so I
用我自己的故事能可以来说明语言的力量
a year ago I wasn't thinking about
一年之前的我从来没有考虑过
anything climate at all sure I read the
任何气候相关的事情
papers I knew that the earth was warming and it was bad
当热，我读报纸知道地球在变暖，这很糟糕
but I kind of lumped it with all the other bad news in the papers and I
但我只是把它当中众多 报纸上的其他坏消息中的一个
didn't particularly relate to it okay
我并没有觉得这件事情与我有关
but now I put solar panels on the roof
但是现在我屋顶上安装了太阳能电池板
we installed the electric vehicle plugs
我们加装了电动车插头
and maybe most important of all
而最重要的
I feel guilty I feel personally connected to the problem
我开始自省，我感到气候问题与我个人息息相关
even when I see my little friend here with his fur coat
甚至当我看到这位 穿着毛衣的小可爱
who hates going out in the summer because of his fur coat
因为太热而不愿意在夏天出去
and loves to have to frolic in the snow
而喜欢在雪中嬉戏的时候
I almost feel the message that
我产生了一种感觉
we can't afford to be messing with the planet
我们不能再这样糟蹋我们的地球了
I just I see these messages everywhere I go
这种感觉几乎时时出现
a year ago the ocean modelers at MIT
一年前，一位麻省理工学院的海洋建模师
came to my office upstairs and
来到我办公室，告诉我
told me about the climber project
关于他们的“攀登项目”的事情
and their goal was to rebuild a state-of-the-art model
他们的目标是要重建一个最先进的模型
of the earth the climate
来模拟地球的气候
what they told me is that what they wanted to do was
他们告诉我说
was write the entire code in Julia
想用Julia来编写整个代码
they told me not to talk them out of it okay
并希望我不要劝退他们
and they're doing this because
他们这样做，是因为
the old codes were just not working for them
老代码跑不起来了
so when it comes to language let me point out
说到语言，我想指出
that philosophers and mathematicians have been talking about the importance of language
哲学家和数学家 一直在谈论语言重要性
for many many years
这贯穿了整个发展的历史
people have known for a long time that
很久以来，人们就知道
language influences us the words
语言影响人类；我们所使用的单词
that we have available changes what we can do
可以改变我们能做的事情
mathematicians like Poincare
庞加莱（Poincare）等数学家
have known for a long time that your choice of notation
一直以来都很知道，人们对于符号系统的选择
can enable new discoveries or
可以带来新的学术发现
constrain new discoveries
亦或者阻碍新的学术发现
and so I'm here to talk about the computer science version of all this and
而我在这里也想讲讲计算机学科中类似的情况
a good programming language design
一种好的编程语言设计
is really applied psychology
着实是心理学的一个应用领域
now again if you think of a programming language
再次提醒，如果你认为
as just a means of
编程语言只是一种
specifying instructions that only a machine can understand
给机器下达指令的方法
then you're not seeing the
那么你就没有看到
real value of modern programming language
现代编程语言的真正价值
modern programming language can now
现代编程语言
be a kind of Applied Psychology
现在可以是心理学的应用对象
it can allow us to create communities of people
它允许我们创建人的相互沟通
who can work together to solve problems
相互协作来解决问题
it can allow us to talk to humans
它可以让我们不仅和机器交流
as well as machines when we want to specify what it is that a climate model
更能与人来交流 告诉别人，一个气候模型、
or an economic model or a political model is doing
经济模型或者政治学模型到底在做什么
it enables all kinds of collaboration of programs
这么做可以实现更广泛的合作
if you have a good programming model
把你的优秀的编程模型 传播开来
and of course for all the complexities of the various kinds of models that we're doing for the earth
当然，由于各种各样的模型的复杂性都日益剧增
everybody these days wants to do high-performance
现在每个人都希望追求更高的程序性能
high performance computing used to be a very small subject
高性能计算之前是一个 非常小的学科
and now it's the sort of thing that everybody wants to do
而它现在这是 每个人都想做的事情
so scientists communicate with math symbols
科学家们使用数学符号来交流的
here I'm showing on the top the kinds of mathematical symbols
我在屏幕上放了一组数学符号
that a climate modeler might put in one of his or her papers right
这是气候学家们会用在 他们的模型里的
so it doesn't matter what the model is saying
模型的内容是什么并不重要
the point is that people communicate with these symbols
重要的是，人们是用这些数学符号来 进行交流，相互理解的
people understand what they're doing with these symbols okay
人们通过读这些符号 来了解别人在做什么
but what does a scientist code typically
但如果科学家要编写代码的话
well you see it right there below the symbols you see
你可以看到屏幕下方
a lot more lines of very very specific instructions
有很多很多行非常繁复严密的代码
and I hope you can see my point
我希望你可以了解到
that it's not very easy to relate back to
这些代码是很难让人回想到上面的符号系统
the symbols if you understand these symbols the code really really doesn't help
如果你知道这些符号的意思 这些代码并不能帮助理解
so the code is really not the math is it
所以实际上，代码并不是数学本身
but with julia we
不过，有了Julia语言
tell people you don't code the math code is the math
我们告诉用户不需要用代码表达公式：代码本身是公式
and so at the highest level
所以大体上来看
if these are the equations that are going to tell you how the climate is changing
如果这些是方程是告诉人们 气候是如何变化的
you want at this level to be able to
你当然希望在代码里
just specify these sorts of symbols
也能用上公式中同样的这些数学符号
right and this code actually runs and
事实上这段代码能跑
implements this model
并且就是计算下面写的这个数学模型的
and we're doing the kind of research that makes it possible
我们正在做的研究，是让人们
to implement this sort of thing
可以做到类似的事情
you could do it on your desktop
你可以台式机上编程
you could do it on a supercomputer
也可以在超级计算机上编程
you could do it on the GPUs that are running very fast and
你也可以在运行非常快的GPU上编程
we've even played a little bit of
我们甚至尝试了一点
with the TPUs, the Google tensor processing units
TPU的工作，谷歌的张量处理单元
my final point and
而我的最后想讲的一点
my most important point is
也是我的本次演讲最重要的要点
what is known as composability
是关于可整合性的
so programming when you program a you write a program for yourself
当你编程时，你自己写了一个程序
and somebody else writes another program
别人也写了一个程序
you might think that they would work together very well
你可能认为这两个程序 可以很好的拼起来一起工作
but they never do
不过事实上这从来不会发生
how many of you have ever had a problem
你们当中有多少人遇到过
with a computer not doing what you wanted it to do
程序不听你使唤的情况？
okay that's probably everybody
大概每个人都遇到过对吧？
right so computers are like that
计算机就是这样的
if you write a program and then
你写一个程序
somebody else writes a program
别人写的程序
with no particular intent for
如果没有很特殊的需求
them working together they usually don't
他们不会把程序拼在一起
because people are able to write programs
而现在，人们可以在很高的层级写程序
at a very high level we find that they
我们发现，他们编写的东西可以拼起来
compose the technical word is composing
专业来说，是可以被整合
which means that these programs can run together
这意味着这些程序可以一起协同运行
and so to give you an example of this composability
我来举个关于可组合性例子
we have this complex interconnected planet you know
我们所在的地球上 各种因素的相互作用十分复杂
we need to work together in much much better ways
我们需要在很多方面共同努力
we have the folks with the CliMA project which I'm showing there on the upper left
我们当中有人在做气候模型 就是屏幕左上角的那些人们
we have economists who are working together to combined with people who do risk modeling
我们有经济学家 我们和做风险建模的人一起协作
there the environmentalists who are tracking the
我们也有环境学家，正在追踪
motions of the animals on the planets energy trading
动物在行星上的运动以及能源交易
we talk about how everybody can play a role
我们常常讨论每一个 个体可以发挥的作用，但是我们
but what we really would like to see is everybody playing this role together
更想看到，每一个个体在共同发挥什么作用
so no more of this
我不希望以后
you sit in your office you write
你坐在自己的小办公室里
your program and you talk about it
写着自己的程序，对他夸夸其谈
somebody else writes a program and they talk about it
别人写一个程序，对它喋喋不休
we're trying to talk about a whole system where everybody can work together
我们希望讨论这一整个系统，而每个人都可以为此出一份力
so the climate modeler the economists a person who's doing an insurance model
因此，不管是气候建模师 经济学家，或者是做保险模型的人
might want to put all of this together
都希望把这一切拼接起来
and see how this can work
来看看能擦出什么样的火花
let me conclude by saying that
最后，我要说的是
what I've learned both personally and professionally is that
在生活和工作中
everybody can play a role in helping to solve the problem of the climate
我发现每个人 都可以在帮助解决气候问题上 出一份力
what I'd like to ask is through personal action
我想要呼吁大家，通过个人的行动
collective action and participating
集体的行动，参与其中
together including through software we
当然也包括软件在内
should all work together to solve the
我们应该共同解决问题
problem of healing the planet thank you
来治愈我们的地球。谢谢大家
[Applause]
[掌声]